The Day I Was Born
"The Day I Was Born!"
Nobi
Oh, my!
Uh...
What's with this big mess?
Um, well... Nobita-kun was looking for the photo album from when he was a baby, and...
A photo album?
Why did he want that?
Who knows...
I bet everyone will say I look so cute!
Shizuka's Growth
Newborn Shizuka
Oh, wow!
Hey, no fair!
You said we'd all look together,
but you started looking without me?!
Dat's cuz yer so slow, Nobita!
We thought you skipped out on us because you only had ugly-looking pictures.
Look, Nobita-san!
The day Shizuka was born
This is a picture from
the day I was born.
I know you'd be cute, Shizuka-chan.
Here's mine!
The Story of Suneo-chan's Birth!
The Story of Suneo-chan's Birth
Wow...
At 5:05 PM...
Suneo-chan Was Born
Suneo-chan was born!
Holding him in my arms
is like holding a real-life angel!
Oh, my baby!
Oh, my Mommy!
Records of Takeshi #1
Dis here is mine!
Now, dun be shocked 'bout
ma' insane amount'a cuteness!
Takka look!
What?!
6/15: The day Takeshi was born
It's shocking, all right...
That looks just like a gorilla...
I'm next. Ta-da!
One month after
Nobi-chan was born
Aren't I pretty cute?
Wut parta dat is cute?
I knew you'd have
a stupid-looking face!
Huh?
One month after
Nobi-chan was born
You think so...?
Huh? What is it?
One month after Nobi-chan was born!
33 days after he was born
34 days after he was born
Hey, Nobita-san...
Hm?
Where's the picture
from the day you were born?
What?
Yoink!
You're right!
Why does this album...
Whoa, there!
Start one month
after  you were born?
Yea! 'Cuz everywun
starts da day their kid's born!
What...?
Maybe they really didn't  want to keep any
pictures of you from right after you were born?
What do you mean?
"Nobi" means "stretch".
I mean, your name's
"Nobi Nobita", right?
They wouldn't have given you such a weird name unless you had a really long, stretched out, stupid-looking face!
Nice wun!
That's going too far!
They must have some reason why.
Wut kinda reason?
Maybe his stupid face
was so ugly, it broke the camera?
What do you mean by that?!
Fine, I'm going to look for the
picture from the day I was born!
And don't be surprised
that I'm SO cute!
So... cute...?
Man, they just
say anything they want.
But why are there no
pictures for a whole month?
Welcome back, Nobi-chan...
I see you went out to play
without doing your homework.
What's more, you
left it extremely messy.
I-I was looking for a picture...
Hey, where's the picture
from the day I was born?
That is NOT what we
are discussing right now!
You have school tomorrow, right?
Wasn't it just the other day that you forgot your homework, and had the teacher scold you?
So go do it
this instant, young man!
But I said I'd do it later.
You always say that, and then
don't do it until the very last minute!
Ugh... I said I'd do it, so I will!
I sure wish you'd trust me more.
Then if I leave you be,
you'll do it on your own, correct?
Yes, of course.
Then do as you please.
Okay!
Then first, I'll go look for
that and go to the vacant lot.
Nobita!
What in the world
are you thinking, Nobita?!
All you ever is give me lip service
with your "I'll study, I'll study."
Your mother is absolutely right!
How about keeping at
least ONE promise you make?!
Honestly, how did you
turn into a boy like this?!
I don't remember
giving birth to a child like this!
What...?
What do you mean, "what"?!
Who on earth did you take after?!
Go think about what you did!
What are you doing, Nobita-kun?
I'm running away from home.
WHAT?!
I finally figured
out the reason why.
It's because I'm
not their real kid!
What kind of nonsense
are you talking about?
But that's the
only thing I can think of!
If I was their real kid, they wouldn't get
mad at me like that or say such awful things!
And I know they would have taken loads of pictures of me the day I was born.
But look at this!
There's no pictures until
a whole month after I was born.
Not a single one!
That's true, but...
Besides...
Y-Yeah...?
My parents wouldn't have
given me a name like "Nobita"!
They would have given
me a way cooler name!
Well now that you mention it,
your name is quite unusual.
Huh?
But isn't "Nobi Nobita" easy to say?
You could say it's pleasing to the ear, and it doesn't have any particularly deep meaning to it. Right?
It doesn't mean anything?
You mean they
just randomly picked it?
I knew it!
I'm not their real kid!
Ah, no! That's not what I meant!
Nobita-kun, that's not it!
This is where we part, Doraemon.
Goodbye!
Wait, Nobita-kun!
But where should I go?
Gian's place...?
Nobita!
Suneo's place...?
You're such a loser, Nobita!
Shizuka-chan's place!
Hey...
There's Shizuka-chan!
Sorry I made you wait.
Come on, let's go.
Okay.
Hey, Mom. Could you tell me
about the time I was born?
Let's see... The weather was great that day,
and it was a nice, quiet morning.
But you were a very lively little bundle of joy,
and started crying really loudly.
I was really surprised at first...
But I was so happy just to
hear that loud voice of yours.
It looks like it's about to rain!
We better get home
before we're drenched!
Aw... It started raining.
What am I gonna do?
I forgot to bring an umbrella!
Mommy, let's hurry home.
Okay, okay.
Neapolitan: Japanese-style spaghetti that is cooked until it's slightly softer than al-dente, then tossed in a mixture of ketchup, sausages, and various vegetables.
What should we have for lunch? Neapolitan?
Yeah! I love Neapolitan!
Oh, I'm so hungry.
I love Neapolitan, too...
Hey, you...
Where did you come from?
Are you all by yourself, too?
I'm all by myself.
Nobita, I'm coming in.
Oh, he's not here?
Wow, looks like it's
really coming down.
Huh?
Nobita-kun!
D-Doraemon!
Nobita-kun, stop being
stubborn, and come home.
Mom said we're
having Neapolitan for lunch!
What?! Really?
No! I'm never going back there!
Why?
Because I already
decided I won't go back!
I'm going to go look
for my real mom and dad!
What is this nonsense?
I mean, just look at you... and your mom.
There's no parent and child
who look more alike than you two!
If that were true...
She would have been worried about me and come to look for me right away!
Oh, where might my
real mother and father be?
Then, do you wanna go check?
What? How?
Let's go back to the day you
were born with the Time Machine!
That's right!
We had that the whole time!
Let's go to the year
and day I was born, August 7!
Here we are!
This is my room, ten years ago!
Gah! It's so hot!
Huh?
This isn't my room.
I wonder why.
Maybe you really
aren't their real kid.
Oh, sorry, sorry!
What I meant to say was...
It's because you
haven't been born yet.
Oh, so that's it.
This must have
been your dad's den.
Wait, no one's here...
Even though this is
the day I'm born, and all...
Where? Where are they?
It's Dad! Dad!
What?
W-Who are you?!
It's me!
That's so mean, how
could you forget your own kid?
Huh...?
What was that all about?
No, more importantly...!
Nobita-kun,
you can't do that.
You haven't been born yet.
Oh, right.
Hey!
Where are you?
Oh, Baby...!
Tamako-san!
What's going on?
I heard my baby was born, so I took off work early, and hurried right home!
Ah!
Yes, this is Nobi.
Oh, this is the nurse?
The baby's not here.
What? Still?
WHAT?!
It's about to be born?!
Got it! I'll be right there!
He must be headed to the hospital!
Yeah!
Whoa!
Hey, wait!
Huh? Where'd Dad go?
Nobita-kun, look at that!
Oh, can I see that one, too?
Dad's buying a camera...
And this is the day
Nobita-kun was born...
So why isn't there
even a single picture of it?
Snap, snap! Snap, snap!
Sna... Oh!
Um, my child is about to be born.
Oh, and this is my first child.
But you need to
be quiet in the hospital.
Yes. I'm sorry.
Ow!
Ah!
It's born...
It's born!
Nobi-san, congratulations! It's a boy.
Oh, thank you for the meal!
Huh?
Uh, no...
I-I mean, thanks...
Go on, go in and see him.
Y-Yes, ma'am!
Nobi Tamako
This is it, Mom's hospital room.
I know it must
have been hard, Mom.
Thank you for giving it your all through it.
The baby is the one
who had to give it his all.
Yes, he did.
He's so cute!
That's right!
I have to take a picture of you
after you were just born.
Look! He just laughed!
Let us see! Let us see!
Ah! Oh! Hey, whoa!
What?! THIS  is me?!
I'm so wrinkled up,
I almost look like a monkey!
Who are you calling a monkey?!
Get out!
We're sorry!
Who were those kids?
They've been hanging
around me for a while, now.
I'd really like to meet the parents
who taught them such bad manners!
Man, that was a surprise...
That's what babies look
like when they're just born.
But it's really sad, because I looked like one of those haniwa clay figures.
Haniwa clay figure: Hollow clay figures made in the 3rd to 6th centuries AD, and used as a funeral ritual.
In modern days, they are appreciated as a form of ancient art.
Oh, yeah... Did you
already let Grandma know?
Yes. She said she had to go
report this to our ancestors right away.
She was crying for joy.
Her face just
lit up with happiness.
Did it?
So what should we
name our little boy?
I've already thought
about that, long and hard.
Oh?
Nobita.
Nobita...
Isn't it a nice name?
It is!
I want them to
give me a cooler name!
I know! I'll let them
know what I want to be called!
No, cut it out!
You'll just get yelled at again!
Huh? A meaning to the name?
Of course there's one.
What?
There, you can see it
perfectly from here, can't you?
That large cherry blossom tree
standing along the river.
I do. What about that tree?
Actually, on the day you told me
we were going to have a baby...
I came to a place
close to here for work.
And that's when I found that tree.
It was still cold at the time, so the tree was
completely bare except for a few dead leaves.
But strangely, there was something about it that attracted me to it.
I wondered what kind of flowers would blossom on it before the child in your tummy would be born...
And actually came to see
that tree countless times.
So that's why you said
you decided on this hospital.
That's right.
I want our child to grow up to
be strong and healthy like that tree...
I want him to grow up to be carefree, excel, and reach new heights.
The name "Nobita"
encompasses those wishes.
"Nobi-nobi" means "to be carefree", and "ta" means "grand" or "magnificent".
It's a wonderful name.
I want him to grow up to be a
straightforward, honest, kind boy.
That's a given!
And if he takes after you, there's no doubt he'll have excellent grades!
And if he takes after you, he'll be a great sportsman with amazing athletic skills.
Or maybe he'll be
good at drawing like you...
And he'll become
a really amazing artist!
It looks like you got all
of your parents' bad traits.
Oh, be quiet.
Maybe Nobita will become
a scholar, or a politician?
Anything's fine, if he becomes
an outstanding member of society.
I want him to be
compassionate, brave...
Cheerful, manly, strong,
pure, upright, handsome...
And above all, a boy
who is kind and easygoing.
Excuse me!
Putting all those expectations
on him kind of puts me in a bind...
You again?!
He's not really that great of a kid.
Yeah, yeah.
What kind of grudge do
you have against our child?!
Get out!
Oh, I'm sorry! I'm sorry!
Look, Nobita-kun!
Hey, I know!
Let's take some pictures!
He said pictures.
I know.
All right, I'll take a lot...
And then tell future Nobita
all about the time he was born.
Hey! Let's come back here
when the cherry blossoms bloom.
All three of us.
I wonder if he'll call me
"Dad" around that time!
Oh, I know!
I'll go take a picture of that
cherry blossom tree, too! Yeah!
Sure is a fine tree.
I wonder if Nobita
will be happy with it.
There...
Where is it?
Where is it? Where'd it go?!
Dad!
That's dangerous, Nobita-kun!
Let me go! Let me go!
I said it's dangerous!
Where's Dad?
Dad!
Dad! Dad...!
Doraemon, save Dad!
Calm down, Nobita-kun!
Um, uh, let's see here...
There it is!
Aw...
The camera I bought with every last bit of money I struggled to save over the past three years...
Now it's ruined...
It's a real shame. We won't have any pictures of Nobita when he was just born...
Let's go home, Nobita-kun.
You understand
everything now, right?
You were loved from the
moment you were born, Nobita-kun.
And you were
their precious treasure.
Yeah.
Oh? What?
Huh?
Nobita-kun, look at that!
Whoa!
It's that cherry blossom tree!
I know!
Let's go!
Wow!
It's so big and tall!
And it's really beautiful!
Well, of course it is.
After all, this tree is
your namesake, Nobita-kun!
Nobita!
Oh?
Nobi-chan!
Nobita!
Mom, Dad!
I'm sorry...
Nobi-chan!
I'm sorry, Nobita.
Huh?
To tell you the truth, I was just
so ecstatic the day you were born...
That I accidentally broke
the camera I had saved up to buy.
But I had wanted to let
you see them no matter what...
Pictures of you when
you were just born, I mean.
Mom had to go through
a lot to give birth to you...
But you had to go
through a lot to be born, too.
You struggled and struggled,
and put all your effort into being born.
And I wanted to explain that to you someday,
while showing you your newborn baby pictures.
But your Mom and Dad will never forget...
The moment that you came into this world,
after going through so much.
Nobi-chan, look at this.
What is it?
Sketches of you, Nobi-chan.
What? Of me?
Your Dad stayed up all night drawing these the day you were born, Nobi-chan.
Even though he did his absolute best to remember the first time he saw you while drawing these, Nobi-chan...
He said they weren't very good,
and had them hiding away all this time.
8/7  The day Nobita was born!
ayatori mitai ni zenbu umaku ikanai
あやとりみたいに　ぜんぶうまくいかない
Just like making string figures,
not everything in life will go well for you.
chanto watasezu ni kongaragattari
ちゃんとわたせずに　こんがらがったり
You might not come across right,
and make things more complicated.
Together with
Mommy
boku wa nigate ya shippai
ボクは　にがてや　しっぱい
I've made mistakes,
have things I'm not good at....
yarusenai kimochi sono mono
やるせないきもち　そのもの
And sometimes feel
helpless and depressed...
kitto daremo ga motteru okubyou na kimochi sono mono
きっとだれもが　もってる　おくびょうなきもち　そのもの
But I'm sure everyone has
felt afraid like that at some point.
Your name is
Nobi
Nobita!
kimi no naka no Nobita ima wa doushite imasu ka?
キミのなかの　のび太　いまはどうしていますか？
Why is the Nobita in you there now?
kokoro no katasumi de naite imasu ka?
こころのかたすみで　ないていますいか？
Is it because you're crying within
the nooks and crannys of your heart?
I love them, Dad!
I'll treasure your drawings forever.
Thank you.
I'm bad at studying,
and I'm no good at sports, either...
I'm not straightforward, not always honest, and I'm always making excuses...
Don't be silly! You just need
to do your best from here on out.
That's right. You might be a
little too easygoing and carefree...
But we're both so
happy we have you, Nobi-chan.
Oh?
Wow!
This is so beautiful!
It really is!
It's grown so much
in the ten years since then.
Just like Nobi-chan.
Now, then...
How about we get a nice
picture of everyone together?
That's fine, but don't we need a camera?
Ta-da!
Okay, I'm taking it. Say cheese!
Cheese!